<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="whitepaper.xsl" ?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>SSL Server Rating Guide</title>
        <releaseinfo>version 2009d (Published in 2009; last update on 9 September
            2013)</releaseinfo>
        <copyright>
            <year>2009-2013</year>
            <holder>SSL Labs (www.ssllabs.com)</holder>
        </copyright>
        <abstract>
            <para>The Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) protocol is a standard for encrypted network
                communication. We feel that there is surprisingly little attention paid to how SSL
                is configured, given its widespread usage. SSL is relatively easy to use, but it
                does have its traps. This guide aims to establish a straightforward assessment
                methodology, allowing administrators to assess SSL server configuration confidently
                without the need to become SSL experts.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Methodology Overview</title>
        <para>Our approach consists of three steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>We first look at a certificate to verify that it is valid and trusted. A
                    server that fails this step is always assigned a zero score.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>We inspect server configuration in three categories:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Protocol support</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Key exchange support</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Cipher support</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The final score&#8212;a number between 0 and 100&#8212;is a combination of the
                    scores achieved in the individual categories. A zero score in any category
                    forces the total score to zero.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Because small differences between configurations are sometimes less important, we also
            assign letter grades to servers. Letter grades are generally more useful&#8212;it is
            instantly clear that a server given an <literal>A</literal> is well configured. <xref
                linkend="table-grades"/> shows how a numerical score is translated into a letter
            grade.</para>
        <table xml:id="table-grades">
            <title>Letter grade translation</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Numerical Score</entry>
                        <entry>Grade</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>score >= 80</entry>
                        <entry>A</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>score >= 65</entry>
                        <entry>B</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>score >= 50</entry>
                        <entry>C</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>score >= 35</entry>
                        <entry>D</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>score >= 20</entry>
                        <entry>E</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>score &lt; 20</entry>
                        <entry>F</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>Our methodology is purposefully designed to be straightforward and practical. Advanced
            users may prefer to dig deep into the finer details of SSL (e.g., which ciphers are
            better than others), but we feel that such an approach, although intellectually
            challenging, would make this guide less useful in practice.</para>
        <section>
            <title>What This Guide Does Not Cover</title>
            <para>Our immediate goal is to focus on those configuration problems whose presence can
                be determined remotely and without manual assessment. It is only a fully automated
                approach that makes it possible to perform a large-scale assessment of SSL
                configuration practices. Our aim is to scan all SSL servers on the public
                Internet.</para>
            <para>In focusing on automation, we have decided not to look for certain problems. We
                will list those problems in this guide, and hopefully find ways to enhance our
                automation to include them in a future version of this guide. Some of those problems
                are listed here:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Certificate quality</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Three certificate types are currently in use: domain-validated,
                            organisation-validated and extended-validation (EV) certificates. This
                            guide requires a certificate to be correct, but does not go beyond this
                            basic requirement. The domain-validated and organisation-validated
                            certificates are generally treated in the same way by the current
                            generation of browser software, and thus offer similar assurance to
                            users. EV certificates are treated significantly better and, generally,
                            they are recommended for high-value web sites. Without a reliable way to
                            determine the purpose of a web site, however, there is little that this
                            guide can do to assess whether a certificate used on an arbitrary site
                            is suitable for the purpose of the site. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Session hijacking issues in web applications</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>There are several ways in which web applications can subvert SSL and
                            make it less effective. For example, session cookies that are not marked
                            as secure can be retrieved by a determined attacker, leading to session
                            hijacking and thus application compromise. Such problems are not the
                            fault of SSL, but they do affect its practical applications
                            nevertheless. Detecting web application&#8211;specific problems is
                            non-trivial to perform in an automated fashion, and this version of the
                            guide does not attempt to do it. We leave this problem for the
                            consideration in the future. In the meantime, to remove any doubt that
                            might exist about the seriousness of the above-mentioned issues, we will
                            state that <emphasis>any application that incorrectly implements session
                                token propagation should be awarded a zero score.</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What Should My Score Be?</title>
            <para>We don&#x2019;t know. In order to tell you whether you&#x2019;ve configured your
                SSL server correctly, we would need to know what your site does. Because different
                web sites have different needs, it is not possible for us to choose any one
                configuration and say that it works for everyone. But we can do two things. First,
                we can give you some general configuration advice and tell you what you should never
                do. Second, we can give you some general guidance using examples of what other web
                sites do. If that&#x2019;s what you are interested in, skip to the end of this
                document for more information. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Is SSL Enough?</title>
            <para>No. A non-trivial web site cannot be secure if it does not implement SSL, but SSL
                is not enough. SSL deals with only one aspect of security, and that is the security
                of the communication channel between a web site and its users. SSL does not and
                cannot address a number of possible security issues that may exist on a web site.
                View SSL as a foundation on which to build, but the foundation alone is not
                enough.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <para>The first version of this guide was written by <link
                    xlink:href="http://blog.ivanristic.com">Ivan Ristic</link>, and subsequently
                enhanced by the contributions from the following individuals, listed in alphabetical
                order: Christian Bockermann, Christian Folini, Robert Hansen, Ofer Shezaf and Colin
                Watson.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Certificate Inspection</title>
        <para>Server certificate is often the weakest point of an SSL server configuration. A
            certificate that is not trusted (i.e., is not ultimately signed by a well-known
            certificate authority) fails to prevent man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacks and renders SSL
            effectively useless. A certificate that is incorrect in some other way (e.g., a
            certificate that has expired) erodes trust and, in the long term, jeopardises the
            security of the Internet as a whole. </para>
        <para>For these reasons, any of the following certificate issues immediately result in a
            zero score:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Domain name mismatch</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Certificate not yet valid</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Certificate expired</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use of a self-signed certificate</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use of a certificate that is not trusted (unknown CA or some other validation
                    error)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use of a revoked certificate</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
            <para>Some organisations create their own (private) CA certificates, a practice that is
                entirely legitimate, provided such CA certificates are distributed, in a safe manner
                (e.g., through the use of customised browsers) to all those who need it. Without the
                access to such certificates we may not be able to verify that a site we are
                inspecting has a trusted certificate, but we believe that such sites will be
                relatively rare. Such issues can be considered on a case-by-case basis.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Scoring</title>
        <para>SSL is a complex hybrid protocol with support for many features across several phases
            of operation. To account for the complexity, we rate the configuration of an SSL server
            in three categories, as displayed in <xref linkend="table-criteria-categories"/>. We
            calculate the final score as a combination of the scores in the individual categories,
            as described in the &#x201c;Methodology Overview&#x201d; section.</para>
        <table xml:id="table-criteria-categories">
            <title>Criteria categories</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Category</entry>
                        <entry>Score</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Protocol support</entry>
                        <entry>30%</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Key exchange</entry>
                        <entry>30%</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Cipher strength</entry>
                        <entry>40%</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>The sections that follow explain the rating system for each of the categories.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Protocol Support</title>
            <para>First, we look at the protocols supported by an SSL server. For example, both SSL
                2.0 and SSL 3.0 have known weaknesses. Because a server can support several
                protocols, we use the following algorithm to arrive to the final score:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Start with the score of the best protocol.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add the score of the worst protocol.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Divide the total by 2.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <table xml:id="table-protocol-support">
                <title>Protocol support rating guide</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Protocol</entry>
                            <entry>Score</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SSL 2.0</entry>
                            <entry>20%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SSL 3.0</entry>
                            <entry>80%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>TLS 1.0</entry>
                            <entry>90%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>TLS 1.1</entry>
                            <entry>95%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>TLS 1.2</entry>
                            <entry>100%</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Key Exchange</title>
            <para>The key exchange phase serves two functions. One is to perform authentication,
                allowing at least one party to verify the identity of the other party. The other is
                to ensure the safe generation and exchange of the secret keys that will be used
                during the remainder of the session. The weaknesses in the key exchange phase affect
                the session in two ways:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Key exchange without authentication allows an active attacker to perform a
                        MITM attack, gaining access to the complete communication channel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Public cryptography is used during key exchange: the stronger the
                        server&#x2019;s private key, the more difficult it is to break the key
                        exchange phase. A weak key, or an exchange procedure that uses only a part
                        of the key (the so-called exportable key exchanges), can result in a weak
                        key exchange phase that makes the per-session secret keys easier to
                        compromise.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table xml:id="table-key-exchange">
                <title>Key exchange rating guide</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Key exchange aspect</entry>
                            <entry>Score</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Weak key (Debian OpenSSL flaw)</entry>
                            <entry>0%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Anonymous key exchange (no authentication)</entry>
                            <entry>0%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Key length &lt; 512 bits</entry>
                            <entry>20%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Exportable key exchange (limited to 512 bits)</entry>
                            <entry>40%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Key length &lt; 1024 bits (e.g., 512)</entry>
                            <entry>40%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Key length &lt; 2048 bits (e.g., 1024)</entry>
                            <entry>80%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Key length &lt; 4096 bits (e.g., 2048)</entry>
                            <entry>90%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Key length >= 4096 bits (e.g., 4096)</entry>
                            <entry>100%</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Cipher Strength</title>
            <para>To break a communication session, an attacker can attempt to break the symmetric
                cipher used for the bulk of the communication. A stronger cipher allows for stronger
                encryption and thus increases the effort needed to break it. Because a server can
                support ciphers of varying strengths, we arrived at a scoring system that penalises
                the use of weak ciphers. To calculate the score for this category, we follow this
                algorithm: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Start with the score of the strongest cipher.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add the score of the weakest cipher.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Divide the total by 2.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <table xml:id="table-cipher-strength">
                <title>Cipher strength rating guide</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Cipher strength</entry>
                            <entry>Score</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>0 bits (no encryption)</entry>
                            <entry>0%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>&lt; 128 bits (e.g., 40, 56)</entry>
                            <entry>20%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>&lt; 256 bits (e.g., 128, 168)</entry>
                            <entry>80%</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>>= 256 bits (e.g., 256)</entry>
                            <entry>100%</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SSL Configuration Advice</title>
        <para>The configuration advice from the original document has been superseded by a
            standalone document with comprehensive coverage of this topic. You can download the
                <link xlink:href="https://www.ssllabs.com/projects/best-practices/">SSL/TLS
                Deployment Best Practices</link> document from the SSL Labs web site.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>For Consideration in Future Releases</title>
        <para>We have left a number of open issues for future consideration:</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Perfect forward secrecy bonus points</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Some key exchange mechanisms allow for perfect forward secrecy. Perfect
                        forward secrecy is a property that ensures that short-term session keys
                        cannot be compromised after a compromise of a long-term secret key (which
                        was used in the generation of the short-term keys). We should consider
                        giving bonus points to those servers that allow only the key exchange
                        mechanisms that allow for forward secrecy.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Differences between encryption algorithms</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Should the choice of encryption algorithms affect server score? For
                        example, it is said that RC4 is not as strong as once thought, so its
                        availability might warrant negative points.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Default ciphers</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In SSL v3 and later, clients provide servers with a list of cipher suites
                        they are willing to use. We want to determine whether servers typically
                        select the first mutually acceptable cipher suite for a session, or if there
                        is a logic behind the suite selection. If the latter, then we might want to
                        consider giving a better grade to the servers that make better choices.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Changes</title>
        <para>We are planning to write a completely new version of the rating guide, building on
            what we have learned from the current version. In the meantime, we are making small
            revisions in order to react to the threats as they come and go.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Changes in 2009c</title>
            <para>In 2009c we have introduced the following changes:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SSL 2.0 is not allowed (F). </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Insecure renegotiation is not allowed (F). </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Vulnerability to the BEAST attack caps the grade to B. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Vulnerability to the CRIME attack caps the grade to B. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The test results no longer show the numerical score (0-100) because we
                        have realized that the letter grade (A-F) is more useful.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>In addition, we've taken the opportunity to remove the old configuration advice,
                directing the readers to our <emphasis><link
                        xlink:href="https://www.ssllabs.com/projects/best-practices/">SSL/TLS
                        Deployment Best Practices</link></emphasis> document instead.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Changes in 2009d</title>
            <para>We no longer require server-side mitigation for the BEAST attack, because we now
                believe that this attack has been sufficiently addressed client-side.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>About SSL</title>
        <para>The Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) protocol is a standard for encrypted network
            communication. It was conceived at Netscape in 1994; version 2.0 was the first public
            release. SSL was later upgraded to 3.0, and, with further minor improvements,
            standardised under the name TLS (<firstterm>Transport Layer Security</firstterm>). TLS
            v1.2, the most recent version, is defined by <link
                xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5246.txt">RFC 5246</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>About SSL Labs</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://www.ssllabs.com">SSL Labs</link> is a computer security
            research organisation that, unsurprisingly, focuses on the SSL standard. Our aim is to
            discuss the rarely mentioned aspects of SSL, promote its correct usage, and generally
            inspire everyone to do their part to promote security. Unlike in some other areas (e.g.,
            application security), security is relatively easy to achieve when it comes to SSL. Thus
            we believe that there are no excuses for a lack of security.</para>
    </section>
</article>
